<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>At a meeting of colored citizens favorable to a call for a State Convention, held in the
            city of Portland, June 11th, 1841, A. N. Freeman in the chair, and J. W. Lewis,
            Secretary, the following preamble and resolution were unanimously adopted. That if
            acting conformably to the will of our Creator in securing our own happiness and the
            happiness of our fellow men, are objects of the highest moment, then we are loudly
            called upon to cultivate and extend the great principles of Virtue and Truth: and
            therefore Resolved, That it is expedient to hold a Convention of the people of color in
            this State the ensuing Fall, for mutual consultation, and the general benefit of our
            people.
         The undersigned were appointed a committe to prepare and issue an address to our
            people.This they submit as A CALL to the Colored citizens of Maine and N. Hampshire.
         Fellow Citizens; We invite your attention to this Call of a State Convention to be held
            in the city of Portland on Wednesday, the 6th day of October next.
         Brethren, we think this meeting ought to be regarded, and hope it will be with peculiar
            interest by every Colored man and woman among us, and no pains spared to render it
            interesting and profitable.
         Our own, our native land demands, our posterity, our enslaved brethren, and our own
            interests for time and eternity, demand an immediate effort for our moral and
            intellectual elevation. The consideration and adoption of the means to these great ends
            we ought no longer to defer.
         As individuals we must mainly achieve our high purposes, yet it is proper and necessary
            for us to embody our efforts.—We shall need all the counsel, sympathy, encouragement and
            strength of union; and by it, with the blessing of God, we may wisely plan, and
            successfully accomplish the mightiest enterprise. We need a nucleus around which may
            gather the moral energy of our whole population: and we beg of you a candid and
            prayerful attention to this matter. Citizens, as you love your country, and would have
            it a mountain of holiness and a dwelling place of righteousnoss, think of the subject
            and come. Fathers, would you have the paths of wisdom, honor and profit opened to, and
            every encouragement given to your beloved offspring to walk in them, consider it well,
            and come. Mothers, withhold not your influence. The characters of Newton, Wesley,
            Whitfield and Washington tell of the powers of maternal influence. We may have noble
            minds among our people.—Exert your influence to furnish occasion and encouragement that
            they may be ornaments to society and blessings to mankind.
         Come all. A trodden down and peeled people ought not to rest. Oppression is not heaven
            inherited by any one. Such a condition is not, cannot be consistent with our duties as
            moral beings. The largest liberty is essential to humanity. The means for our full
            emancipation are within our reach; and we cannot longer refuse to use them, and be
            innocent.
         The subjects which will come up for consideration and action, are many and great. In a
            "Call" we can of course allude, and briefly too, to but a part of them.
         Next to our personal relations to our Heavenly Father, the subject of Education should
            interest us. We cannot measure its importance, but we feel it in our relations to man.
            And the power it has given to others, it offers to us. Through the goodness of God
            knowledge is held to our lips and we may drink even to that which is life eternal. It
            has no prejudices, but whosoever will, may come.
         We are identified with the poor, suffering, bleeding slave of the South. He is our
            brother. The claims of kin are added to the claims of humanity upon us to labor directly
            and heartily with the philanthropist, to undo the heavy burdens and let the oppressed go
            free. The condition of our enslaved brethren greatly affects our own. We cannot expect
            the full enjoyment of all our rights while the influence of Slavery is felt in our
            land.
         The baneful influence of intemperance has been felt by multitudes among us. Prejudice
            is, alas! too strong without any cause. None of us, therefore, by intemperance or any
            vicious indulgence, should contribute in the least to foster it. Temperance is proving a
            blessing to all who embrace her. Elevating and purifying, her ways are pleasantness, and
            her paths peace. And in her ways alone is there certainty of final triumph.
         We would also ask your attention to the important subject of the future occupations of
            our offspring. The employment naturally affects the disposition and mind as well as the
            condition. Some corrupt the principles; others contract the mind ; while others leave
            its powers stagnant. If such employments do not degrade they cannot have an elevating
            tendency. Our aims require that their minds and hearts be guarded from all evil
            influences; that their occupations be favorable to the developement and cultivation of
            the mind; consistant with sound principle; such as generate enlarged views and generous
            sentiments; and such as will render them as useful as their talents will permit. Such
            desirable employments there are, and some of them are open to us.
         It is neccessary that we should have all the statistical information we can procure in
            regard to our numbers, occupations, and resources, and benevolent and other societies
            supported among us. And we hope every one will come prepared to give such
            information.
         Brethren, Our enterprise is a great one, and will demand the influence and labor of
            every one. None can be spared. And none we trust will increase our difficulties by their
            indifference. Our brethren in other States are moving in this cause. Come, let us take
            counsel together; encourage each others' heart; strengthen each others' hand; and
            planting, in humble relience upon the Great Deliverer, await the sun and shower of his
            favor, and the plentiful harvest.
         Yours truly, for truth and right, A. N. FREEMAN, J. W. LEWIS, A. W. NILES, Com.</ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
